Finding Aid for Allan Schreiber papers, 1968-1988
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Allan Schreiber papers 1968-1988
Schreiber, Allan.
06103 Aa 2
Allan Schreiber, a teacher at Pioneer High School in Ann Arbor, was part of an initiative in the 1970s to develop an alternative high school, known as Earthworks. Schreiber was a teacher and the head of Earthworks for most of its existence. The papers include materials on Earthworks background and history, founding and planning materials, correspondence, materials on the merger with Community High School, printed works and annual reports, evaluations and studies of the school, field trip logs, and audiovisual material.
2.4 linear feet
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
The records were donated by Allan Schreiber (donor no. 9103 ) in July 2006.
The collection is open to research.
Allan Schreiber, a teacher at Pioneer High School in Ann Arbor, was part of an initiative in the 1970s to develop an alternative high school, known as Earthworks. The impetus for an alternative educational program partly stemmed from a period of social unrest during the late 1960s and early 1970s at Pioneer. Racial tensions as well as perceived threats to freedoms of expression and speech incited student protests and rioting. Perceiving a need for change, Ray Silverman, a teacher at Pioneer, proposed an alternative education program that would take place in the portable classrooms behind the high school, emphasizing student-led curriculum development and governance. At the time, Silverman's proposal was dismissed.
The alternative high school concept took shape upon the arrival of new school superintendent, Bruce McPherson, who was a strong supporter of alternative education. In 1971, about sixty faculty and students at Pioneer proposed the idea of an alternative school, known as Pioneer Two. The school board approved and Pioneer Two began in October 1971 with an enrollment of 108 students. Schreiber, then a teacher at Pioneer, did not join the faculty of Pioneer Two until 1972, frustrated from the lack of interest that faculty at Pioneer had in making changes. Schreiber was immediately asked to head Pioneer Two.
The educational experience at Pioneer Two aimed to go beyond the traditional classroom. Students were encouraged to propose their own educational curriculum. Students did not have graduation requirements and grading was on a pass/fail basis. The school also offered non-traditional classes and expanded students' education beyond the classroom, in the form of school field trips. The school was renamed Earthworks in 1972, inspired by a field trip to Indian mounds in southern Ohio.
A decline in student enrollment and a lack of support from school administrators led to the decline of Earthworks in the mid-1970s. In 1978, administrators proposed that Earthworks be merged with Community High School, another alternative high school in Ann Arbor. In the fall of 1978 Earthworks became part of Community High School. Earthworks soon after fell out of existence as students and programs became part of the new high school. Schreiber left the Ann Arbor Public Schools after the first year that Earthworks merged with Community High.
For a detailed history of Earthworks, researchers may want to consult Allan Schreiber's personal account of Earthworks' history written in 1988 (found in the first folder of the collection.)
The papers include materials on Earthworks background and history, founding and planning materials, correspondence, materials on the merger with Community High School, printed works and annual reports, evaluations and studies of the school, field trip logs, and audiovisual material.
The papers also include one folder of material on spring 1968 disturbances at Pioneer collected by Nicholas Schreiber, Allan Schreiber's father and principal of Pioneer High School in the 1960s.
The papers contain the following series: Background and Planning, Correspondence, Merger, Evaluations, Reunion, Printed Material, School Logs, and Audiovisual Material.
Subjects:
Schreiber, Allan.; Earthworks (School: Ann Arbor, Mich.); Community High School (Ann Arbor, Mich.); Alternative schools--Michigan--Ann Arbor.; Schools--Michigan--Ann Arbor.; Pioneer High School (Ann Arbor, Mich.)
Subjects - Visual Materials:
Schreiber, Allan.; Earthworks (School: Ann Arbor, Mich.); Alternative schools--Michigan--Ann Arbor.; Schools--Michigan--Ann Arbor.; Students--Michigan--Ann Arbor.; Teachers--Michigan--Ann Arbor.; School field trips--Michigan--Ann Arbor.
Contributors:
Schreiber, Nicholas.
Genre Terms:
Motion pictures.; Photographs.
- Background and planning 1968-1988
  The Background and Planning series (1968-1988) includes materials documenting the background and history of Earthworks, including clippings on the school, a history of the school written by Allan Schreiber, and various files relating to Pioneer High School unrest in the late 1960s and early 1970s. Planning documents consist of early founding material, including various proposals for alternative high schools and later Earthworks' planning documents.
  - Background and history
    - Earthworks history 1988 (Box 1)
    - Clippings (Box 1)
    - Pioneer High School unrest
      - Nicholas Schreiber's file on spring 1968 disturbances (Box 1)
      - September 30, 1970 file (Box 1)
      - Student unrest, Fall 1971 (Box 1)
      - Meetings, memos, correspondence, etc. 1969-1970 (Box 1)
  - Planning
    - Pre-Earthworks correspondence 1969-1971 (Box 1)
    - Early founding material 1971 (Box 1)
    - In-service plan 1976-1977 (Box 1)
    - Secondary Alternatives Coordinating Council (SACC) 1977 (Box 1)
- Correspondence (Communications)
  The Correspondence series (1971-1977) includes various communications dealing with various aspects of the school during the period of its development, growth, and decline.
  - 1971-1977, 5 folders (Box 1)
- Merger 1972-1979
  The Merger series (1972-1979) includes materials relating to the proposed merger with Community High School, including concerns, planning, and discussions.
  - Community High founding blueprint circa 1972 (Box 1)
  - Community High School concerns (pros and cons of becoming department of CHS) 1975-1977 (Box 1)
  - Merger pre-planning 1977-1978 (Box 1)
  - Merger planning 1977 (Box 1)
  - Post-merger 1978-1979 (Box 1)
- Evaluations 1972-1977
  Various studies of the concept and inner-workings of the Earthworks school can be found in the Evaluations (1972-1977) series, which includes evaluations of the school from outside evaluators as well as evaluations and comments from Earthworks' students and faculty.
  - Mid-year evaluation 1972 (Box 1)
  - Studies/assessments by "outsiders," 1972-1974 (Box 1)
  - In-house evaluation 1973-1974 (Box 1)
  - Bureau of School Services 1974 (Box 1)
  - Self-evaluation, fall 1974 (Box 1)
  - Marbles game, Len Svransky paper, (Earthworks, Huron High School, St. Thomas) 1974-1975 (Box 1)
  - Questionnaire responses, Pioneer High School-Huron High School, Fall 1975 (Box 1)
    (summary of responses)
  - Evaluation proposal 1976 (Box 1)
  - Student responses, in-house evaluation 1976 (Box 1)
  - Ann Arbor needs more alternative programs, Allan Schreiber, circa 1976-1978 (Box 1)
  - Ann Arbor Pioneer High School North Central Report: team visit to Pioneer, March 15-17, 1977 (Box 1)
  - "Official" evaluation by E. Brzezinski (evaluation specialist) 1977 (Box 1)
  - Testimonials 1977 (Box 1)
  - Evaluations undated (in-house and visitors) (Box 1)
- Reunion 1975, 1982
  The Reunion series (1975 and 1982) consists of correspondence relating to efforts to put together several Earthworks reunions.
  - Christmas reunion 1975 (Box 2)
  - Correspondence 1982 (Box 2)
- Printed Material 1972-1978
  The Printed Works series (1972-1978) contains various printed works produced at Earthworks. The series contains forms and handouts, annual reports from 1972 to 1975, as well as student publications and works and a newsletter covering the activities at Earthworks, entitled On the Fritz.
  - Annual reports 1972-1975 (Box 2)
  - Forms and handouts 1974-1977 (Box 2)
  - Forms and library journal (Box 2)
  - Newsletter On the Fritz
    - 1973-1974 (Box 2)
    - 1975-1976 (Box 2)
    - 1976-1977, 2 folders (Box 2)
    - 1978 mock-up (Box 2)
  - Student publications (Box 2)
    ("Alternative Education in a Pluralistic Society" with essay by AS)
- School Logs 1972-1977
  The School Logs (1972-1977) were taken on school trips and students and teachers were encouraged to make contributions covering any topic or thought. The logs were once kept in three-ring binders and have been preserved in their original order. Although described and arranged by date, the logs may not necessarily be chronological.
  - 1972-1973, 2 folders (Box 2)
    (folder 1 includes log of trip to Toronto)
  - 1973 fall (Box 2)
  - 1974-1975, 2 folders (Box 2)
  - 1976 spring (Box 2)
  - 1976-1977, 2 folders (Box 2)
  - 1977, 2 folders (Box 2)
  - River trip (Box 2)
  - Fragments (trips to Niagara-Toronto, camping on AAPS wilderness property, Innisfree) (Box 2)
- Visual materials 1973-1978
  The Visual Materials (1973-1978) include photographs documenting Earthworks activities both in the school as well as on various field trips. The series also includes films of a student dance concert and a student-created animation.
  - Photographic negatives
    - Dickson Museum, Anderson Lake October 19, 1973 (Box 3)
    - Dickson Museum logos/Lincoln's New Salem undated (Box 3)
    - Jim Rees undated (Box 3)
    - School, dance, arboretum undated (Box 3)
    - School, feet, etc. undated (Box 3)
    - St. Genevieve undated (Box 3)
  - Slides
    - Earthworks Fritz Building April 1974, March 1977, November 1976 (Box 3)
    - Earthworks trips
      - AAPS property May 1974 (Box 3)
      - Anekan (?) Mounds, caves, South Ohio October 1974 (Box 3)
      - Silver Lake Dunes, Hartwick Pines 1975 (Box 3)
      - Upper Peninsula October 1976 (Box 3)
      - Ohio Indian mounds June 1977 (Box 3)
  - Photographs/negatives
    - At the Fritz building (Box 3)
    - Earthworks activities at the Fritz building circa 1974-1977 (Box 3)
      (assorted and misc. contact sheets, negatives, prints)
    - Earthworks camping trip to evaluate Ann Arbor Public Schools property (near Clare, MI?) (Box 3)
  - Films
    - Dance concert by students June 9, 1978 (Box 3)
    - Earthworks animation film undated (Box 3)